[music]
>> Time's up.
>> They don't make them like Independence
Day anymore. Yes, super expensive sci-fi
blockbusters still exist with stacked
casts of A-list celebs implausibly
trotting the globe, hopping between
action-packed set pieces while cracking
wise. Those aren't going anywhere, but
when it comes to the science of special
effects, the handmade scale model
apocalypse of Independence Day was the
triumphant last gasp of a vanishing
craft. The know-how is still there, and
in a world of 3D printers, the physical
hurdles to miniature effects [music]
have surely been lowered, but CGI is
simply faster, more flexible, and
infinitely easier to change your mind
about, especially [music] on a modern
blockbuster where films are frantically
revised until the last possible second.
It's much less of a hassle to redesign a
superhero suit in post or spice up a
computer-generated sky beam than it is
to build a 14-ft model out of plaster
and blow it up [music] with 40 explosive
charges.
Dozens of painstakingly detailed
miniatures are detonated throughout
[music] Independence Day, also known for
copyright reasons as ID4, in a wave of
destructive annihilation that defined
the summer of 1996 more than the
Macarena. The film's flagship image of
an exploding White House was so potent
that Fox bet their entire marketing
strategy around it, saving [music] the
debut for one of the most impactful
Super Bowl ads in modern history.
[music] It was an image destined to
become immortalized on a lenticular VHS
cover, but a lot of things had to come
together to destroy the pretend people's
house. A lot of money, a lot of talent,
and a lot of extremely flammable tiny
furniture with just one [music] chance
to pull it off.
ID4 was hand-built from scratch and
blown up spectacularly in a feat of
practical magic that we may never see
again. This is the special effects story
of the last time Hollywood did it the
hard way. Let's kick the tires and light
the fires because this is Independence
Day, the last handmade blockbuster.
>> That's what I call a close encounter.
>> I think when you do a special effects
movie, I think you should do something
which First of all, you have to go to
the limits of what technology can do,
and you have to create sequences that
people haven't seen.
>> 1996 was a big year for close encounters
of the mass-market sci-fi kind. Mulder
and Scully sizzled. Michael and Bugs
beckoned us to join them in a cosmic
jam, and Jack Nicholson was unalived by
cackling CGI Martians twice. The digital
future was arriving like an alien
invasion force, and everyone could feel
it, including Hollywood.
>> [music]
>> Computer graphics were already a fixture
of the VFX pipeline by '96, no longer a
novelty but a legitimate tool.
Pioneering films like Terminator 2 and
Jurassic Park had offered a glimpse into
what was possible, and it was only a
year removed from Toy Story, the first
full-length computer-animated feature.
It was abundantly clear that CGI was
here to stay, but it wasn't the answer
to everything just yet, at least not
according to Roland Emmerich and Dean
Devlin. Fresh off the surprise success
of Stargate, a modestly budgeted space
saga that punched well above its weight
at the box office,
>> [music]
>> Emmerich and Devlin hatched their
follow-up film in a rented house in
Mexico. They emerged after a month with
a finished screenplay and full
storyboards of what would become
Independence Day. Tired of the old
tropes of secret alien encounters in
cornfields and pastures, the two
envisioned ID4 as an in-your-face
extraterrestrial orgy of destruction
with flying saucers that stretched for
miles, blotting out the skies above
Earth's major cities. Getting their idea
greenlit was easy. After a brief bidding
war, Fox bought the script and blessed
it with a $75 million budget, which
seems like small potatoes by today's
standards when a musical biopic can cost
$200 million.
Still, [music] director Emmerich and
producer Devlin had a huge task on their
hands, far beyond anything they'd
accomplished before.
>> We shot over 6,000
elements to make up over 400 visual
effect shots. Now, to give perspective
on that, our last film Stargate, which
is thought of as a a effects-heavy
movie, had roughly 260 visual effect
shots. So, this is over 140 shots more.
Oh, and in those shots we had an average
of about three elements per shot, and
here we're averaging [music] 10 to 15
elements per shot.
>> One would think that pulling off an
achievement on such a massive scale
would require the latest in CGI
technology, a full embrace of the future
that had begun to reshape movie making.
Instead, Emmerich relied on something
more reliable, more convincing, and as
it turned out, considerably cheaper.
They would make ID4 the old-fashioned
way and use the new tech to bring it all
together into an unforgettable summer
blockbuster. And it all started on the
moon.
>> It's coming from the moon.
>> Devlin and Emmerich's philosophy is
fully evident from the very first shot
of the film, the placid [music] silence
of the Apollo 11 lunar landing site. As
Neil Armstrong's legendary lines echo
from our speakers, we see his footprints
in the dust slowly begin to disappear,
swallowed by a shadow creeping across
[music] the surface. An enormous
mothership passes overhead, dwarfing the
iconic Star Wars flyby by orders of
magnitude, emitting a mysterious [music]
signal that wakes up a bunch of
character actors and tells them to start
the movie.
>> A radio signal from another world.
>> [music]
>> Today, a shot like this would almost
certainly be entirely digital, and ID4
probably could have pulled it off in
1996. The moon is a harsh mistress,
after all, and its bleak, textureless
gray, and lack of organic life wouldn't
[music] have been too difficult to
render 30 years ago. But, that's not
what Independence Day did. Instead, the
crew built a physical lunar surface 6 m
wide and 8 m deep, lit with 60,000 W of
light to simulate single sun source
unblemished by atmosphere. They placed
small models with clever forced
perspective and rigged a tiny motor to a
wooden board to simulate a moonquake
that makes the famous footprints vanish.
It's a solution that would have made the
real Apollo engineers proud, the people
who landed men on the moon with nothing
but slide rules and computers with less
processing power than most modern
greeting cards. Their tools were
primitive, but their ingenuity wasn't.
>> One of the things Roland has taught me
from the first day I started working
with him is it's not the tool, it's the
craft.
And we would approach every special
effect shot on the simplest way to do it
first, the tried-and-true, the simplest,
easiest way. Only when that wouldn't
work, would you go up to the next level.
And when that wouldn't work, you go to
the next level.
>> The production set up shop in Culver
City, California, commandeering a
massive aircraft manufacturing plant
that once belonged to Howard Hughes.
Most of what they built in those
cavernous buildings were eventually
destroyed, but first, they would have to
be designed.
Patrick Tatopoulos is behind some of the
most memorable and polarizing production
designs in modern blockbusters. [music]
His visual style embodies the end of
history arrogance of the '90s, the butt
rock malaise of the 2000s, and beyond.
It's hard to believe that the timeless
look of ID4 came from the same brain
that birthed Godzilla 1998 and [music]
Batman v Superman.
>> Alien world is nothing you can really
potentially start from, and definitely
not start from other people's work. You
try to avoid that and not get stuck in
somebody else's style. So, usually when
I do alien
stuff, any alien material, I'll try to
just start from scratch, let myself go.
>> Given free reign of the design of the
alien harvesters and their massive tech,
Tatopoulos kept things fairly simple,
taking centuries of cultural [music]
obsession with flying saucers and little
green men and ordering it super-sized.
>> We wanted to tap into pre-existing
mythology about [music] UFOs.
Because people somehow have an idea of
what an alien might look like or what a
spaceship looks like [music] or what
that you know, all these things would
be. So, what we try to do is show you
that and then take it a step beyond it.
Have it look familiar and then as you
see it closer say it's one step farther.
It's It's It's wilder than I had
imagined.
>> Spaceship design had progressed a lot
since the days of dangling hubcaps on
strings, but the complex kit-bashed
structure of a Nostromo or Battlestar
wouldn't read as large on screen as
something far more elemental.
>> The simpler is the shape, the more
massive the element looks like. And
[music] actually, working for those
designs, I started to really realize
that actually the simple shape makes the
thing looks much more massive. And
that's At that point, our direction was
told that that thing, thinking, "Okay,
simple, elegant, and massive."
>> It's counterintuitive, but it's a
time-tested visual trick going back to
the Imperial [music] battle cruisers and
tiny rebel fighters of Star Wars. We
need context and contrast [music]
to understand scale, and there's nothing
like seeing tiny swarms around a vast
simple surface to sell something as
genuinely enormous. How big are we
talking here? We've got hard numbers on
the Bulbas mothership.
>> Now, we estimate that it has a diameter
of over 550 km and a mass roughly 1/4
the size of our moon.
>> But the real stars of Independence Day,
Jeff Goldblum and Bill Pullman aside,
[music]
are the devastating and aptly named city
destroyers. Each one is 15 mi wide with
enough firepower to vaporize any trace
of human civilization in a similar
radius. To put that in perspective,
that's 15 times wider than a Star
Destroyer and roughly 37 Enterprise D's
stretched end to end. The destroyers
were real physical [music] objects
hand-built in three different sizes. A
4-ft version, a 12-ft version, and a
30-ft mid-scale model that represented a
sixth of the ship and was so large it
couldn't fit inside the model shop. All
fitted with thousands of inconspicuous
[music]
details to give the behemoths a
techno-organic heaviness. They are
fantastic models and they're on screen
for a lot of ID4's runtime, often in
broad daylight. We almost get used to
them as part [music] of the backdrop
before nightfalls on July 2nd. Now, a
city destroyer carries its killing blow
on its underbelly, blossoming open with
a mechanical grace before obliteration.
The crew called it the schism, and they
made it happen with a 10-ft wide,
[music] 10-ft high mechanism that only
opened upside down. Each shot of the
schism could take a day across multiple
passes with lighting that had to be
timed precisely to accommodate the CGI
laser beam. Models were filmed via
motion control, cameras spinning around
a stationary object to simulate precise
movement under replicable conditions.
The The various elements were filmed
multiple times over in many layers from
lights and shadows to [music]
atmospheric smoke passes for maximum
reality.
>> One of the beauties of compositing is
that rather than trying to do everything
in camera, trying to do everything live
where you would have to have a model,
you'd have to have a spaceship to scale,
you'd have to have pyro and all of that
happening at the [music] same time. By
compositing in layers, it allows us to
choreograph each layer perfectly
>> [music]
>> and then put them together.
>> Spending thousands to capture plates and
pyro means living with your decisions.
You don't get a second chance to
incinerate this caliber of single-use
scenery.
>> What it really is offering
when everything is evaluated is
flexibility. So, if somebody's shooting
model miniatures, having an FA team,
let's say. Once that's shot, the
lighting, everything [music] as the way
it was shot, they're locked into it. So,
that by the time you go to put that
element together way down the line 6
months later, then all of a sudden the
director says, "Oh, guess what? I've
changed my mind. This isn't a day scene.
It's now a night scene." It's extremely
difficult cuz you're locked into certain
parameters. Whereas with
computer-generated imagery, you have
control of the lighting, you have
control of it just the way you would in
a in a shooting environment. [music] So,
flexibility is really what digital has
to offer the filmmakers.
>> The CGI era was obviously approaching
fast, but some analog techniques still
can't be topped. To create the burning
skies and fiery clouds when the
destroyers enter the atmosphere, Devlin
and Emmerich repurposed a huge water
tank left over from Stargate and pumped
in [music] white tempera paint through
thin submerged pipes. Filmed at 360 FPS,
the diffusing paint creates an organic,
dynamic, almost dreamlike effect that
even renderers today have trouble
pulling off. Effects like these are
physical and fractal [music] and chaotic
and there's often no substitute for the
real thing. See also explosions. [music]
>> Jesus.
>> [music]
>> For 9 months while Will Smith and Jeff
Goldblum were improvising on set and
Robert Loggia was wondering what he'd
gotten himself into, model supervisor
Mike Joyce and his team were holed up in
their Hughes hangar building models that
put the Spruce Goose to shame.
>> There's more miniatures in this movie
than probably any two movies combined.
There's cities to build, there's alien
craft, alien creatures. It just runs the
whole gamut.
>> 25 model makers, three sculptors, and
four painters were put to work creating
spacecraft, [music]
landmarks, and entire city blocks all
destined to be destroyed. Patriotic
monuments got all the press, but ID4 has
more architectural cannon fodder [music]
than many Kaiju movies. It's no wonder
the gang got back together for Godzilla.
But, what goes up must come crumbling
down. So, Emmerich and Devlin enlisted
one of Hollywood's most trusted
demolition experts to pull the trigger,
[music]
master pyromancer Joe Viskocil, the man
who blew up the Death Star.
Computers have gotten a lot better at
capturing the fractal nature of real
explosions, but on a visceral level they
pale in comparison to the concussive
thump of fiery detonations and
splintered [music] wood. Nowhere is this
more evident than the fully CGI
mothership explosion, a dated sour note
in the fat lady's swan song.
>> [music]
>> I think in what we're doing, miniatures
work best. I mean, there's a lot of
explosions, a lot of pyro, a lot of
fire, a lot of stuff that
even today with the sophisticated
computers is still tricky to do.
>> When you uh blow up a big model, there's
nothing better than that. You can't
create this like a CGI, yet.
>> AND ACTION.
>> IN THE EARLY MORNING HOURS OF JULY 3RD,
1996 at 2:32 a.m. Eastern time, the
Harvesters countdown triggered a global
cataclysm that murdered millions of
humans and spared at least one dog.
Everything blows up exquisitely in ID4
[music] with the Empire State Building
as a particular standout. Timed charges
run down the models full facade in a
sequence so oddly satisfying in its
perfection that the crew [music] flipped
the footage upside down and reused it
for the climactic collision between
[music] the schism AND RANDY QUAID.
>> HELLO, BOYS.
I'M BACK.
>> THE signature practical effect of the
checkmate sequence, minus a certain
exploding seat of government, was the
wall of destruction rolling down crowded
city streets. Emmerich Devlin [music]
were told it couldn't be done.
>> Pretty much every effect person we
talked to said, "Be prepared for a
$150,000 shot." We said, "Well, why is
it so difficult to do?" And they said,
"Well, cuz not only do you have to shoot
the street and shoot all the elements of
the street that happen, but you'll have
to digitally create the fire that rolls
down the street and then digitally
composite [music] that into your shot.
And that's going to be very expensive to
make that look real." And Roland said,
"Well, why can't we just do that all in
camera?"
>> [music]
>> And everyone said, "Well, it'll look
fake. It'll never work." And Roland
said, "I I I I think I think I could do
that in camera."
>> But how do you control fire, which
rather famously rises up and funnel it
down a horizontal street? You don't.
>> And then you look down the street.
[music]
You wanted that the fire comes right at
you, but fire wants to go up, especially
like when you do it in a miniature. So,
what we had to do is we had [music] to
build streets and objects upright. The
The street had to become pretty much a
chimney for the fire.
>> Each street model was constructed at
1/24 scale, 8 ft wide and 20 ft long,
dressed with details designed to
withstand strict scrutiny under the
all-seeing lens of cameras wrapped in
[music] flame-retardant material and
pointed directly down the length of 5th
Street and Grand.
>> We have the detail from bottom to top,
all the signs, all the telephone poles,
all the street lights,
>> parking meters. It basically has
everything [music] on it.
>> We really have to be careful that the
best detail is directly in front of the
camera.
>> We'll shoot a blue screen. [music]
There will be air cannons and stuff like
a concussion wave hitting them, then
we'll shoot debris, and then we'll do
some live-action stuff [music] and some
people in it.
>> Emmerich got the $150,000 shots he
dreamed of for just $30,000 a pop thanks
to his vertical thinking. But miniatures
were only part of the madness. The
devastation called for hundreds of
extras and dozens of full-sized vehicles
flung across the screen. Emmerich used
them as punctuation, hurling a bus or
fire truck directly into the frame to
cut [music] between sequences.
>> I know in one day alone in New York we
crashed 23 cars.
>> [screaming]
>> All of it, the practical pyro, the scale
models, the doomed citizens, were
captured [music] in separate elements
and layered together in post. Six units
shooting simultaneously to create a
singular unforgettable opera of
obliteration in just 4 minutes of film.
>> So it is very complicated, but if you
get it right it looks fantastic.
>> In any other summer blockbuster, the
encroaching cliff of fire engulfing all
humanity would be the signature defining
image of the entire film. But Devlin and
Emmerich had other plans.
>> [music]
>> Roland Emmerich had a very simple idea
for how to sell Independence Day. He
wanted to blow up the White House and
broadcast it to the entire world. And
that's easier said than done for a
variety of reasons, least of all was
Fox's reluctance to destroy such a
beloved building on national television.
The US was only a few months removed
from the Oklahoma City bombing and a
federal building exploding on primetime
television made studio execs somewhat
understandably nervous. Devlin's
counterargument was hard to refute. It's
space aliens. Fox tested two versions of
the teaser, one with the White House and
one without, and they were so blown away
that they not only endorsed the
wholesale destruction of 1600
Pennsylvania Ave, they pegged the ad for
a prestigious and pricey spot in Super
Bowl 30. Fans were going into the game
with a sense of dread after a string of
boring blowouts, but the big game
actually delivered. Between the
Pittsburgh [music] Steelers pushing the
Cowboys to the wire in what would turn
out to be the last championship of the
Dallas dynasty and a killer halftime
show from Queen of Motown Diana Ross, it
was the most watchable Super Bowl in
years. But the biggest showstopper was
the 30 seconds of carnage capped with a
flying saucer vaporizing the White
House. From the earliest days of cinema,
we've seen every portico and pillar of
the White House recreated [music] for
the screen, creating a primal craving
baked into the societal psyche to see it
reduced to a crater on celluloid. The
White House is such a filmic space that
Fox already had sets for the Oval Office
and Roosevelt Room just lying around,
used in two previous presidential movies
and redressed for the Whitmore
administration. The interiors would live
to see another day as would this facade
built for the evacuation scene. That
final honor would go to a massive,
expensive model, Mike Joyce's piece de
resistance, 9 months in the making.
>> [music]
>> Mike Joyce and his team of geniuses sat
down and built this unbelievable replica
of the White House. Given the
familiarity with the real deal, the
miniature, if a 5-ft tall behemoth could
be called that, couldn't skip on the
details or the size.
>> We're building that at 12 scale, which
is over 14 ft [music] wide, and we're
going to blow it up, and it'll look
tremendous when it goes.
>> This had to be
>> [music]
>> world-class product because all the
cameras that we're setting up around
here are within 10 ft of of of this
particular model.
>> I think, you know, the best White House
model ever.
We put a lot of lot of thinking into
that. We build it not like out of wood,
we build it out of plaster. Everything
was a mold. So, every piece, you know,
was like created first in wood and then
made a silicone mold out of it and then
little plaster pieces, and then it was
built like the White House was built out
of single [music] pieces.
>> The model was so convincing that the
production used it for forced
perspective, avoiding a costly location
shoot by filming real extras marching in
front of a fence with the miniature set
100 ft back, reading as the actual
building. It was a masterpiece of
miniature making that cost a lot of
money to create, and they only made one.
Putting everything on the line would be
a lot of pressure for the average
pyromaniac, but after pulling the
trigger on the Death Star and nuking Los
Angeles in Terminator 2, the White House
demolition was squarely in Joe
Viskocil's wheelhouse.
>> Today, we are doing the explosion of the
White House.
>> This model probably cost in excess of
$50,000. I get one shot at it.
There's a great many [music] variables
that go into the completion and the
successful blowing of a model like
[music] this. One has to consider what
the model is made out of, in this case,
plaster. You have to know the scale, you
have [music] to know the size of the
charges that you're using, how much gas,
what the camera speeds are. Even though
you're shooting 300 frames per second,
[music]
if I was to use something like dynamite,
you would have maybe two frames of
explosion and that's it. [music] You
want to blow it up in stages and you
want to see the pieces and debris flying
out of there.
>> The White House um has got such great
detail in it that even in the most
preliminary uh test that we've done,
that the White House holds up in an
extreme close-up. So, all of a sudden
this this particular miniature is very
near and dear to our hearts because it's
got such wonderful detail.
I don't know if I really want to blow it
up.
>> [laughter]
>> The crew had come to love the giant hunk
of plaster that had been hanging around
Hughes Aircraft with them all these many
months. And more than a few people
weren't ready to see it destroyed. At
least the model would have company on
the day of its oblivion. Fox turned
demolition day into a press event and
built bleachers for journalists to
witness the Viking funeral.
>> That's clear, please.
>> When you start to come down to that
10-minute [music] mark, everybody's very
concerned because of course there's
hundreds and hundreds of hours tens of
thousands of dollars and what we really
want to do [music] is make sure that we
just don't stub our toe at the last
moment. We really only want to do this
once.
>> Roll camera. Roll cameras, please.
>> Hey!
HEY!
AND ACTION!
>> IT IS EVERYTHING THAT I EXPECTED it to
be and uh everything went off. [music]
We didn't have any problems. The timing
was right, the debris was right,
fireball was perfect.
And this is what's left of it.
>> And we blew the sucker up with nine
cameras shooting it at various speeds
and then we digitally [music] composited
that into our shot uh FROM WASHINGTON.
>> HEY!
AND ACTION!
>> 95 MILLION PEOPLE watched the White
House explode at the Super Bowl and even
more would see it in the coming months
of the all-encompassing ad campaign.
Phone lines around the country were tied
up for hours downloading a postage stamp
sized QuickTime file of the proto-viral
ad. [music]
By the time the film was released seven
months later, the shot was already
iconic. Independence Day is full of
moments we've carried with us far beyond
the summer of '96, but more than Will
Smith chomping a stogie, more than Brent
Spiner being asphyxiated, more than the
Fruitopian machine in Jeff Goldblum's
office, it's this image, barely six
seconds of screen time, that has become
synonymous with the summer blockbuster
as a whole. It was the birth of modern
trailer culture, where work prints and
con exclusive footage are leaked weeks
in advance, and we're bombarded on
social media with teasers for teasers.
It was also ground zero for trailers
being unfinished and ever so slightly
deceptive. The helicopter caught in the
explosion doesn't appear in the original
ad. It was a new era of filmmaking
slowly taking shape just as an old one
was headed out to pasture.
>> I think old-fashioned effects, you know,
will never die out because they're
simply too good.
>> There's still plenty of CGI in
Independence Day. The dog fights are
largely digital and look fantastic, and
the shield and energy beam effects
haven't aged a bit. Some of the
compositing is a little sus. The odd CGI
explosions stand out like a sore
low-resolution thumb, and Boomer's leap
of salvation is just as preposterous
today as it was in 1996, but overall,
ID4 is an extremely successful blend of
new technology and tried and tested
tactility that rightly earned an Oscar
for its achievement.
>> Our film does everything from the
highest-tech digitally animated,
digitally composite CGI shot to little
models on wires in front of photo
backings, and everything in between.
>> Independence Day is a film with one foot
in the future and the other in an
airplane hangar full of plaster and
gasoline. What Devlin, Emmerich,
Viscosil, Joyce, and their crews
accomplished was, by any measure, a
staggering triumph in craft that
contains the entire history of visual
effects within a crowd-pleasing package.
Not bad for one take.
>> [music]